Mark Twain summed up what I take to be
لخص مارك توين ما أعتبره أنا
one of the fundamental problems of cognitive science
إحدى المشاكل الأساسية بالعلوم الإدراكية
with a single witticism.
بروح دعابية فريدة.
He said, "There's something fascinating about science.
فقال: "هناك أمر مدهش في العلوم.
One gets such wholesale returns of conjecture
حيث نحصل على جملة من الأفكار
out of such a trifling investment in fact."
مقابل استثمار بسيط من الافتراض."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Twain meant it as a joke, of course, but he's right:
بالطبع كان توين يمزح ولكنه كان محقاً.
There's something fascinating about science.
هناك أمر مدهش حول العلوم.
From a few bones, we infer the existence of dinosuars.
حيث أثبتنا من بضعة عظام وجود الديناصورات.
From spectral lines, the composition of nebulae.
ومن الخطوط الطيفية مكونات السديم.
From fruit flies,
ومن ذباب الفاكهة
the mechanisms of heredity,
آليات الوراثة،
and from reconstructed images of blood flowing through the brain,
ومن إعادة بناء صور لتدفق الدم عبر الدماغ،
or in my case, from the behavior of very young children,
أو في حالتي، من سلوك الأطفال الصغار،
we try to say something about the fundamental mechanisms
نحاول التوصل إلى شيء ما حول الآليات الأساسية
of human cognition.
بالإدراك البشري.
In particular, in my lab in the Department of Brain and Cognitive Sciences at MIT,
وخاصة، في مختبري بقسم الدماغ والعلوم الإدراكية في معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنيات،
I have spent the past decade trying to understand the mystery
حيث قضيت العِقْد الماضي أحاول فهم لغز
of how children learn so much from so little so quickly.
كيفية تعلم الأطفال الكثيرمن القليل وبسرعة.
Because, it turns out that the fascinating thing about science
لأنه تبين أن المدهش في العلوم
is also a fascinating thing about children,
هو أيضا أمر مدهش في الأطفال،
which, to put a gentler spin on Mark Twain,
ولَمْسَة مارك توين بالضبط،
is precisely their ability to draw rich, abstract inferences
هي قدرتهم لاستخلاص نتائج غنية ومجردة
rapidly and accurately from sparse, noisy data.
بسرعة ودقة من معطيات متفرقة ومشتتة.
I'm going to give you just two examples today.
سأقدم لكم اليوم مثالين فقط.
One is about a problem of generalization,
واحد حول مشكلة التعميم
and the other is about a problem of causal reasoning.
والآخر حول مشكلة الاستدلال السببي.
And although I'm going to talk about work in my lab,
رغم أني سأتكلم حول العمل في مختبري،
this work is inspired by and indebted to a field.
إلا أن هذا العمل مستلهم من مجال أدين له بالكثير.
I'm grateful to mentors, colleagues, and collaborators around the world.
وأنا ممتنة لكافة المرشدين والزملاء والمتعاونين حول العالم.
Let me start with the problem of generalization.
دعوني أبدأ بمشكلة التعميم.
Generalizing from small samples of data is the bread and butter of science.
التعميم انطلاقًا من معطيات بسيطة هو أساس العلوم.
We poll a tiny fraction of the electorate
فنحن نستطلع آراء نسبة ضئيلة من الناخبين
and we predict the outcome of national elections.
ونتوقع نتائج انتخابات وطنية.
We see how a handful of patients responds to treatment in a clinical trial,
ونرى كيفية استجابة حفنة من المرضى للعلاج في التجارب السريرية،
and we bring drugs to a national market.
فنزود السوق الوطنية بالأدوية.
But this only works if our sample is randomly drawn from the population.
لكن الأمر ينجح فقط إذا أخذنا عينة عشوائية من السكان.
If our sample is cherry-picked in some way --
فإذا نحن أخذنا العينة بطريقة منتقاه
say, we poll only urban voters,
كأن نستطلع فقط الناخبين بالمجال الحضري،
or say, in our clinical trials for treatments for heart disease,
أو فلنقل، في تجاربنا السريرية الخاصة بعلاجات أمراض القلب،
we include only men --
نختار فقط الرجال
the results may not generalize to the broader population.
فإن النتائج لن تعمم إلى السكان على نطاق واسع.
So scientists care whether evidence is randomly sampled or not,
لذلك يهتم العلماء ما إذا كانت العينة مأخوذة بشكل عشوائي أم لا،
but what does that have to do with babies?
ولكن ما علاقة ذلك بالرضع؟
Well, babies have to generalize from small samples of data all the time.
لأن الرضع عليهم دائماً أن يعمموا انطلاقاُ من بيانات مأخوذة من عينات صغيرة.
They see a few rubber ducks and learn that they float,
لأنهم يرون بعض البط المطاطي فيتعلمون أنها تطفو،
or a few balls and learn that they bounce.
أو بضع كرات فيتعلمون أنها ترتد.
And they develop expectations about ducks and balls
فيطورون توقعات حول البط والكرات
that they're going to extend to rubber ducks and balls
فيتعرفون على خصائص البط المطاطية والكرات
for the rest of their lives.
لبقية حياتهم.
And the kinds of generalizations babies have to make about ducks and balls
وأنواع التعميم التي على الرضع القيام بها فيما يتعلق بالبط والكرات
they have to make about almost everything:
يطبقونها تقريبًا في كل شيء:
shoes and ships and sealing wax and cabbages and kings.
الأحذية والسفن وشمع الختم والملفوف والملوك.
So do babies care whether the tiny bit of evidence they see
فهل يهتم الرضع بمعرفة ما إذا كانت العينة الصغيرة التي يرونها
is plausibly representative of a larger population?
تمثل في الظاهر أكبر عدد من السكان؟
Let's find out.
دعونا نكتشف ذلك.
I'm going to show you two movies,
سأعرض عليكم فيديوهان،
one from each of two conditions of an experiment,
كل واحد منهما عن حالة من حالتي التجربة،
and because you're going to see just two movies,
ولكونكم ستشاهدون فيديوهان فقط،
you're going to see just two babies,
فستشاهدون فقط رضيعان.
and any two babies differ from each other in innumerable ways.
ويختلف كلا الرضيعان عن بعضهما بطرق لا تعد ولا تحصى
But these babies, of course, here stand in for groups of babies,
وبالطبع يمثل هذان الرضيعان هنا مجموعة من الرضع،
and the differences you're going to see
والاختلافات التي ستشاهدونها
represent average group differences in babies' behavior across conditions.
تمثل معدل مجموعة الاختلافات بسلوك الرضع في كل الظروف
In each movie, you're going to see a baby doing maybe
ستشاهدون في كل فيديو رضيعاً يقوم ربما
just exactly what you might expect a baby to do,
بما تتوقعونه بالضبط من رضيع أن يفعله،
and we can hardly make babies more magical than they already are.
ومن الصعب أن نجعل الرضع أكثر سحراً مما هم عليه بالفعل.
But to my mind the magical thing,
لكن باعتقادي الشيء الساحر،
and what I want you to pay attention to,
وما أريدكم أن تنتبهوا إليه،
is the contrast between these two conditions,
هو التناقض بين هذين الظرفين،
because the only thing that differs between these two movies
لأن الأمر الوحيد المختلف بين هذين الفيديوهين
is the statistical evidence the babies are going to observe.
هو الدليل الإحصائي الذي سيلاحظه الرضيعان.
We're going to show babies a box of blue and yellow balls,
وسنقدم لهما صندوق كرات زرقاء وصفراء،
and my then-graduate student, now colleague at Stanford, Hyowon Gweon,
وستسحب(هيوون غويون)، طالبتي المتخرجة حديثا والزميلة الحالية بجامعة ستانفورد،
is going to pull three blue balls in a row out of this box,
3 كرات زررقاء على التوالي من هذا الصندوق،
and when she pulls those balls out, she's going to squeeze them,
وعند سحبها خارجًا ستضغط عليها
and the balls are going to squeak.
فتصدر أصواتًا.
And if you're a baby, that's like a TED Talk.
وإذا كنتم رُضعًا، فإن الأمر كمحادثة تيد.
It doesn't get better than that.
لن يكون الأمر أفضل مما هو عليه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the important point is it's really easy to pull three blue balls in a row
ولكن النقطة الأهم هي أنه من السهل سحب 3 كرات زرقاء على التوالي
out of a box of mostly blue balls.
من صندوق معظم كراته زرقاء.
You could do that with your eyes closed.
بإمكانكم فعل ذلك وأنتم مغمضي العينين.
It's plausibly a random sample from this population.
وهي في الظاهر عينة عشوائية من السكان.
And if you can reach into a box at random and pull out things that squeak,
وإذا كانت معظم الأشياء التي تسحبونها من الصندوق بشكل عشوائي تصدر أصواتاً،
then maybe everything in the box squeaks.
فلربما أن يكون كل ما بالصندوق يصدر أصواتاً.
So maybe babies should expect those yellow balls to squeak as well.
ولربما سيفترض الرضع أن الكرات الصفراء أيضا تصدر أصواتاً.
Now, those yellow balls have funny sticks on the end,
إلا أن الكرات الصفراء بها عصي مضحكة عند الطرف،
so babies could do other things with them if they wanted to.
لذا يمكن للأطفال أن يفعلوا بها أشياء أخرى إن أرادوا ذلك.
They could pound them or whack them.
ويمكنهم رميها أو الضرب بها.
But let's see what the baby does.
ولكن دعونا نشاهد ماذا يفعل الرضيع.
(Video) Hyowon Gweon: See this? (Ball squeaks)
(الفيديو) هيوون غويون: أرأيت هذه؟ (كرة تصدر صوتاً)
Did you see that?
هل رايت ذلك؟
Cool.
رائع!
See this one?
أنظر إلى هذه؟
(Ball squeaks)
(كرة تصدر صوتاً)
Wow.
واو
Laura Schulz: Told you. (Laughs)
لورا شولتز: لقد أخبرتكم. (ضحك)
(Video) HG: See this one? (Ball squeaks)
(الفيديو) هيوون: أرأيت هذه؟ (كرة تصدر صوتاً)
Hey Clara, this one's for you. You can go ahead and play.
(كلارا) هذه واحدة من أجلك. بإمكانك أخذها واللعب بها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
LS: I don't even have to talk, right?
لورا: حتى أنه لا داعي لأتكلم، صحيح؟
All right, it's nice that babies will generalize properties
حسناً، من الجيد أن الرضع يعممون خصائص
of blue balls to yellow balls,
الكرات الزرقاء على الصفراء،
and it's impressive that babies can learn from imitating us,
ومن المدهش أنهم يتعلمون من خلال تقليدنا،
but we've known those things about babies for a very long time.
ولكن نحن نعرف كل هذه الأشياء عن الرضع منذ وقت طويل،
The really interesting question
السؤال المهم حقاً هو
is what happens when we show babies exactly the same thing,
ما الذي يحدث عندما نري الرضع نفس الشيء،
and we can ensure it's exactly the same because we have a secret compartment
ويمكننا التأكيد على أنه نفس الشيء لأنه لدينا حجرة سرية
and we actually pull the balls from there,
والحقيقة أننا نأخذ الكرات من هناك،
but this time, all we change is the apparent population
لكن هذه المرة، كل ما تغير هو عموم السكان
from which that evidence was drawn.
الذي أخذت منه العينة.
This time, we're going to show babies three blue balls
وهذه المرة، سنري الرضع 3 كرات زرقاء
pulled out of a box of mostly yellow balls,
مأخوذة من صندوق أغلب كراته صفراء اللون،
and guess what?
واحزروا ماذا؟
You [probably won't] randomly draw three blue balls in a row
من المرجح أن لا تسحبوا بشكل عشوائي 3 كرات زرقاء على التوالي
out of a box of mostly yellow balls.
من الصندوق أغلب كراته صفراء.
That is not plausibly randomly sampled evidence.
إنها ليست عينة عشوائية في الظاهر.
That evidence suggests that maybe Hyowon was deliberately sampling the blue balls.
وتفترض هذه العينة أنه فد تكون (هيوون) اختارت عن عمد عينة من الكرات الزرقاء.
Maybe there's something special about the blue balls.
وربما أن هناك شيء ما مميز في الكرات الزرقاء.
Maybe only the blue balls squeak.
وربما أن الصوت يصدر فقط من الكرات الزرقاء.
Let's see what the baby does.
دعونا نرى ماذا يفعل الرضيع.
(Video) HG: See this? (Ball squeaks)
(الفيديو) هيوون: أرأيت هذه؟ (كرة تصدر صوتاً)
See this toy?
أرأيت هذه اللعبة؟
Oh, that was cool. See? (Ball squeaks)
كان هذا ممتعاً، أرأيت؟ (كرة تصدر صوتاً)
Now this one's for you to play. You can go ahead and play.
والآن هذه واحدة من أجلك للعب بها. بإمكانك أخذها واللعب بها.
(Fussing) (Laughter)
(همهمة الرضيع) (ضحك)
LS: So you just saw two 15-month-old babies
لورا: كان هذان رضيعان عمرههما 15 شهراً
do entirely different things
يقومان بأشياء مختلفة تماماً
based only on the probability of the sample they observed.
إعتمادًا على احتمالية العينة التي لاحظاها.
Let me show you the experimental results.
دعوني أُريكم النتائج التجريبية.
On the vertical axis, you'll see the percentage of babies
على المحور الرأسي، تشاهدون النسبة المئوية من الرضع
who squeezed the ball in each condition,
الذين يضغطون على الكرة في جميع الحالات،
and as you'll see, babies are much more likely to generalize the evidence
وكما ستشاهدون، في الغالب يميل الرضع إلى تعميم العينة
when it's plausibly representative of the population
عندما تمثل في الظاهر السكان
than when the evidence is clearly cherry-picked.
بدلا من تلك التي اُختيرت بعناية.
And this leads to a fun prediction:
وهذا يقود إلى تكهن ممتع:
Suppose you pulled just one blue ball out of the mostly yellow box.
لنفترض أنكم سحبتم كرة زرقاء واحدة من صندوق معظم كراته صفراء.
You [probably won't] pull three blue balls in a row at random out of a yellow box,
فلن تسحبوا على الأرجح 3 كرات زرقاء بشكل عشوائي من الصندوق الأصفر،
but you could randomly sample just one blue ball.
ولكن يمكنكم أن تسحبوا بعشوائية كرة زرقاء واحدة فقط.
That's not an improbable sample.
هذه ليست عينة مستبعدة.
And if you could reach into a box at random
وإذا أمكنكم أن تسحبوا من صندوق عشوائي
and pull out something that squeaks, maybe everything in the box squeaks.
شيء ما يصدر صوتاً، فلربما أن كل ما فيه يصدر صوتاً أيضاً.
So even though babies are going to see much less evidence for squeaking,
لذا حتى وإن كان الرضع سيلاحظون عينات أقل تصدر الأصوات،
and have many fewer actions to imitate
وسيكون لديهم أفعال أقل بكثير لمحاكاتها
in this one ball condition than in the condition you just saw,
في هذه الحالة مع كرة واحدة فقط بدلا من الحالة التي شاهدتموها للتو،
we predicted that babies themselves would squeeze more,
توقعنا أن الرضع أنفسهم سيصدرون أصواتاً أكثر،
and that's exactly what we found.
وهذا ما حدث بالضبط.
So 15-month-old babies, in this respect, like scientists,
الرضع في عمر 15 شهراً، في هذا الصدد، هم كالعلماء،
care whether evidence is randomly sampled or not,
يهمهم معرفة ما إذا كانت العينة عشوائية أم لا،
and they use this to develop expectations about the world:
ويستخدمون ذلك لتطوير توقعاتهم عن العالم:
what squeaks and what doesn't,
ما يصدر صوتاً وما لا يصدره،
what to explore and what to ignore.
ما يمكن استكشافه وما ينبغي تجاهله.
Let me show you another example now,
دعوني أريكم مثلاً أخر،
this time about a problem of causal reasoning.
وهذه المرة حول مسألة الاستدلال السببي.
And it starts with a problem of confounded evidence
وتبدأ بمسألة العينة الدخيلة
that all of us have,
التي نتعرض لها جميعاً،
which is that we are part of the world.
لكوننا جزء من العالم.
And this might not seem like a problem to you, but like most problems,
وقد لا يبدو لكم ذلك كمشكلة بالنسبة لكم، ولكن كأغلب المشاكل،
it's only a problem when things go wrong.
لا تصبح مشكلة إلا عندما تسوء الأمور.
Take this baby, for instance.
خذوا هذا الرضيع مثلاً.
Things are going wrong for him.
تسير الأمور على نحو سيء معه.
He would like to make this toy go, and he can't.
إنه يود أن يشغل اللعبة ولكنه لا يستطيع.
I'll show you a few-second clip.
سأريكم مقطع من بضع ثواني.
And there's two possibilities, broadly:
وعلى العموم، هناك احتمالان:
Maybe he's doing something wrong,
ربما أنه يقوم بشيء خاطئ،
or maybe there's something wrong with the toy.
أو ربما هناك خطب ما في اللعبة.
So in this next experiment,
وفي التجربة القادمة،
we're going to give babies just a tiny bit of statistical data
سنقدم للأطفال القليل فقط من المعطيات الإحصائية
supporting one hypothesis over the other,
لدعم فرضية على أخرى،
and we're going to see if babies can use that to make different decisions
وسنرى إذا كان بإمكان الرضع استخدام تلك المعطيات لاتخاذ قرارات مختلفة
about what to do.
حول الذي ينبغي فعله.
Here's the setup.
هذه هي المسألة.
Hyowon is going to try to make the toy go and succeed.
ستحاول (هيوون) جعل اللعبة تعمل وستنجح في ذلك.
I am then going to try twice and fail both times,
وسأحاول أنا مرتين وأفشل في ذلك،
and then Hyowon is going to try again and succeed,
وستحاول (هيوون) مرة أخرى وتنجح في ذلك،
and this roughly sums up my relationship to my graduate students
وهذا يلخص نوعاً ما علاقتي بطلابي المتخرجين
in technology across the board.
في مجال التكنولوجيا مع الجميع.
But the important point here is it provides a little bit of evidence
لكن النقطة المهمة هنا هي تزويدها للأطفال بالقليل من الأدلة
that the problem isn't with the toy, it's with the person.
بأنه ليس هناك خطب في اللعبة بل في الشخص.
Some people can make this toy go,
بعض الناس يمكنهم تشغيل هذه اللعبة،
and some can't.
والبعض لا.
Now, when the baby gets the toy, he's going to have a choice.
الآن، عندما يحصل الرضيع على اللعبة سيكون لديه الخيار.
His mom is right there,
والدته حاضرة هناك،
so he can go ahead and hand off the toy and change the person,
لذا يمكنه أخذ اللعبة وتقديمها لتغيير الشخص،
but there's also going to be another toy at the end of that cloth,
ولكن ستكون هناك لعبة أخرى أيضاً في نهاية ذلك القماش،
and he can pull the cloth towards him and change the toy.
ويمكنه سحب القماش نحوه وتغيير اللعبة.
So let's see what the baby does.
لذا دعونا نرى ماذا يفعل الرضيع.
(Video) HG: Two, three. Go! (Music)
(فيديو) هيوون: اثنان، ثلاثة، انطلق! (موسيقى)
LS: One, two, three, go!
لورا: واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، انطلق!
Arthur, I'm going to try again. One, two, three, go!
آرثر، سأحاول مرة أخرى. واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، انطلق!
YG: Arthur, let me try again, okay?
آرثر، دعني أحاول مرة أخرى، حسنا؟
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Look at that. Remember these toys?
انظر إلى هذا. هل تذكر هذه الألعاب؟
See these toys? Yeah, I'm going to put this one over here,
هل ترى هذه الألعاب؟ سأضع واحدة هناك،
and I'm going to give this one to you.
وسأعطيك هذه.
You can go ahead and play.
يمكنك البدء في اللعب.
LS: Okay, Laura, but of course, babies love their mommies.
لورا: حسنا، يا لورا، بطبيعة الحال الرضع يحبون أمهاتهم.
Of course babies give toys to their mommies
ومن الطبيعي أن يقدم الرضع اللعب لهن
when they can't make them work.
عندما لا يستطيعون تشغيلها.
So again, the really important question is what happens when we change
ومرة اخرى، السؤال المهم بالفعل هو ما الذي يحدث عندما نغير
the statistical data ever so slightly.
المعطيات الإحصائية قليلاً.
This time, babies are going to see the toy work and fail in exactly the same order,
في هذا المرة، سيشهد الرضع على تشغيل اللعبة وتوقفها على التوالي،
but we're changing the distribution of evidence.
ولكن سنغير توزيع الأدلة.
This time, Hyowon is going to succeed once and fail once, and so am I.
في هذه المرة، ستنجح (هيوون) بتشغيلها مرة وتفشل مرة وكذلك أنا.
And this suggests it doesn't matter who tries this toy, the toy is broken.
والغرض من ذلك أنه لا يهم من يجرب تشغيل اللعبة، لكونها معطلة أصلاً.
It doesn't work all the time.
فهي لا تعمل بتاتاً.
Again, the baby's going to have a choice.
مجددًا، سيكون أمام الرضيعة الخيار.
Her mom is right next to her, so she can change the person,
ووالدتها بجانبها، لذا بإمكانها تغيير الشخص،
and there's going to be another toy at the end of the cloth.
وتوجد لعبة أخرى عند نهاية القماش.
Let's watch what she does.
دعونا نشاهد ماذا تفعل.
(Video) HG: Two, three, go! (Music)
(فيديو) هيوون: اثنان، ثلاثة، انطلق! (موسيقى)
Let me try one more time. One, two, three, go!
دعيني أحاول مرة أخرى. واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، انطلق!
Hmm.
هممم.
LS: Let me try, Clara.
لورا: دعيني أحاول، كلارا.
One, two, three, go!
واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، انطلق!
Hmm, let me try again.
همممم، دعيني أحاول مجددًا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
HG: I'm going to put this one over here,
هيوون: سأضع هذه هناك،
and I'm going to give this one to you.
وأعطيك هذه.
You can go ahead and play.
بإمكانك البدء باللعب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
LS: Let me show you the experimental results.
لورا: اسمحوا لي بعرض النتائج التجريبية.
On the vertical axis, you'll see the distribution
على المحور الرأسي، ستشاهدون توزيع
of children's choices in each condition,
خيارات الأطفال وفق كل حالة،
and you'll see that the distribution of the choices children make
وستلاحظون بأن توزيع الخيارات التي قام بها الأطفال
depends on the evidence they observe.
تتوقف على الأدلة التي لاحظوها.
So in the second year of life,
لذا في السنة الثانية،
babies can use a tiny bit of statistical data
يمكن للأطفال استخدام القليل من المعطيات الإحصائية
to decide between two fundamentally different strategies
ليختاورا بين استراتيجيتين مختلفتين جوهرياً
for acting in the world:
للتصرف في العالم حولهم:
asking for help and exploring.
كطلب المساعدة والاستكشاف.
I've just shown you two laboratory experiments
لقد عرضت عليكم للتو تجربتين مخبريتين
out of literally hundreds in the field that make similar points,
من بين المئات التي تتوصل إلى نتائج مماثلة في هذا مجال،
because the really critical point
لأن النقطة المهمة بالفعل
is that children's ability to make rich inferences from sparse data
هي أن قدرة الأطفال على الاستنتاج انطلاقاً من معطيات قليلة
underlies all the species-specific cultural learning that we do.
هي وراء كافة أنواع التعلم الثقافي الذي نقوم به.
Children learn about new tools from just a few examples.
الأطفال يتعلمون عن أدوات جديدة من أمثلة قليلة فقط.
They learn new causal relationships
يتعلمون عن علاقات سببية جديدة
They even learn new words, in this case in American Sign Language.
ويتعلمون حتى كلمات جديدة، في هذه الحالة لغة الإشارة الأمريكية.
I want to close with just two points.
أريد أن أختم بنقطتين فقط.
If you've been following my world, the field of brain and cognitive sciences,
إذا كنتم متابعين لعالَمي، مجال علوم الدماغ والإدراك،
for the past few years,
خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية،
three big ideas will have come to your attention.
فإن ثلاث أفكار كبيرة ستلفت انتباهكم.
The first is that this is the era of the brain.
الأولى، أن هذا هو مجال الدماغ.
And indeed, there have been staggering discoveries in neuroscience:
والواقع، كانت هناك اكتشافات مذهلة في علم الأعصاب:
localizing functionally specialized regions of cortex,
كتحديد موقع مناطق متخصصة وظيفياً بالقشرة،
turning mouse brains transparent,
وجعل دماغ فأر يصبح شفافاً،
activating neurons with light.
وتفعيل الخلايا العصبية بواسطة الضوء.
A second big idea
الفكرة الثانية الكبيرة
is that this is the era of big data and machine learning,
هو أنه عهد البيانات الضخمة والتعلم الآلي،
and machine learning promises to revolutionize our understanding
ويعد التعلم الآلي بإحداث ثورة في مفهومنا
of everything from social networks to epidemiology.
حول كل شيء انطلاقاً من شبكات التواصل الاجتماعي.
And maybe, as it tackles problems of scene understanding
وربما، لكونه يتناول مشاكل فهم المشهد
and natural language processing,
ومعالجة اللغة الطبيعية،
to tell us something about human cognition.
لتخبرنا بشيء حول الإدراك البشري.
And the final big idea you'll have heard
والفكرة الختامية الكبيرة التي ستسمعونها
is that maybe it's a good idea we're going to know so much about brains
أنه ربما ستكون فكرة جيدة التعرف أكثر على الدماغ
and have so much access to big data,
والوصول بهذا الشكل إلى المعطيات الضخمة،
because left to our own devices,
لأنه إذا تُرِكْنَا لأجهزتنا،
humans are fallible, we take shortcuts,
فإن البشر مُعرضون لخطأ، ونحن نختصر،
we err, we make mistakes,
ونضل، ونخطئ،
we're biased, and in innumerable ways,
ومتحيزين، بطرق لا تعد ولا تحصى،
we get the world wrong.
ونفهم العالم بشكل خاطئ.
I think these are all important stories,
وأعتقد بأن جميعها قصص مهمة،
and they have a lot to tell us about what it means to be human,
ولديهم الكثير ليخبرونا به حول معنى أن نكون بشر،
but I want you to note that today I told you a very different story.
لكن أريدكم أن تلاحظوا بأني أخبرتكم اليوم بقصة مختلفة جداً.
It's a story about minds and not brains,
قصة حول العقل وليس الدماغ،
and in particular, it's a story about the kinds of computations
ولاسيما، قصة حول أنواع العمليات الحسابية
that uniquely human minds can perform,
التي بإمكان العقل البشري وحده تنفيذها،
which involve rich, structured knowledge and the ability to learn
والتي تتطلب معارف غنية وبنيوية وقدرة على التعلم
from small amounts of data, the evidence of just a few examples.
انطلاقاً من معطيات قليلة، وأدلة عن بضعة أمثلة.
And fundamentally, it's a story about how starting as very small children
وهي في الأساس قصة حول كيفية البدء كطفل صغير جداً
and continuing out all the way to the greatest accomplishments
والاستمرار في السير على الطريق للوصول إلى أعظم إنجازات
of our culture,
ثقافتنا،
we get the world right.
وهي الفهم الصحيح للعالم.
Folks, human minds do not only learn from small amounts of data.
فالعقل البشري لا يتعلم فقط من كميات صغيرة من المعطيات.
Human minds think of altogether new ideas.
بل إنه يخلق أيضاً أفكار جديدة.
Human minds generate research and discovery,
فالعقل البشري يولد البحوث والاكتشافات،
and human minds generate art and literature and poetry and theater,
وكذلك الفن والأدب والشعر والمسرح،
and human minds take care of other humans:
كما أنه يعتني بغيره من البشر:
our old, our young, our sick.
بكبيرنا، وصغيرنا، ومريضنا.
We even heal them.
بل إننا نُطَبِّبُهُم،
In the years to come, we're going to see technological innovations
وخلال السنوات القادمة، سنشهد ابتكارات تقنية
beyond anything I can even envision,
تتخطى كل ما أستطيع تصوره،
but we are very unlikely
لكن من غير المحتمل
to see anything even approximating the computational power of a human child
أن تقترب من القوة الحسابية للطفل البشري
in my lifetime or in yours.
سواء في حياتي أو في حياتكم.
If we invest in these most powerful learners and their development,
إذا استثمرنا في هؤلاء المتعلمين النجباء وتنمية قدراتهم،
in babies and children
في الرضع والأطفال
and mothers and fathers
والأمهات والأباء
and caregivers and teachers
ومقدمي الرعاية والمعلمين
the ways we invest in our other most powerful and elegant forms
فبناءً على الطرق التي نستثمر بها في أقوى وأجمل الأشكال
of technology, engineering and design,
التقنية والهندسية والتصميمية التي لدينا،
we will not just be dreaming of a better future,
فلن نكون فقط نحلم بمستقبل أفضل،
we will be planning for one.
بل سنكون بدأنا بالتخطيط له.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Laura, thank you. I do actually have a question for you.
كريس اندرسون: لورا، شكرا لك. الحقيقة لدي سؤال من أجلك.
First of all, the research is insane.
في البداية، هذا بحث غير معقول.
I mean, who would design an experiment like that? (Laughter)
أعني، من صمم تجربة من هذا القبيل؟ (ضحك)
I've seen that a couple of times,
رأيت هذا بضع مرات،
and I still don't honestly believe that that can truly be happening,
بصراحة، مازالت لا أصدق أن هذا يحدث حقا،
but other people have done similar experiments; it checks out.
ولكن هناك أشخاص آخرين قاموا بتجارب مماثلة. والنتيجة متشابهة.
The babies really are that genius.
بالفعل، إن الرضع عباقرة.
LS: You know, they look really impressive in our experiments,
لورا: أتعلم، إنهم حقاً يثيرون الإعجاب في تجاربنا،
but think about what they look like in real life, right?
ولك أن تتخيل ما يفعلونه في الحياة الواقعية، صحيح؟
It starts out as a baby.
يبدأ كرضيع.
Eighteen months later, it's talking to you,
وبعد 18 شهرا، يتحدث معك،
and babies' first words aren't just things like balls and ducks,
والكلمات الأولى للرضع ليست فقط كرات وبط،
they're things like "all gone," which refer to disappearance,
بل أشياء مثل "لقد ذهبت" كإشارة على الاختفاء،
or "uh-oh," which refer to unintentional actions.
أو "أو-أو" للإشارة إلى أحداث غير مقصودة،
It has to be that powerful.
عليها أن تكون قوية.
It has to be much more powerful than anything I showed you.
بل أكثر قوة من أي شيء أريتكم إياه.
They're figuring out the entire world.
إنهم يفهمون العالم بأكمله.
A four-year-old can talk to you about almost anything.
بل يمكن لطفل في الرابعة من عمره أن يحدثك تقريباً عن كل شيء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: And if I understand you right, the other key point you're making is,
كريس: إن كان فهمي صحيحاً. أنت تهتمين بنقطة مهمة و هي
we've been through these years where there's all this talk
بأننا تحدثنا كثيراً خلال السنوات الأخيرة
of how quirky and buggy our minds are,
حول مدى حماقة و شذوذعقولنا،
that behavioral economics and the whole theories behind that
وأن الاقتصاد السلوكي وجميع نظرياتها التي
that we're not rational agents.
تؤكد بأننا لسنا عوامل عقلانية.
You're really saying that the bigger story is how extraordinary,
فإنك تؤكدين على روعة هذه القصة العظيمة،
and there really is genius there that is underappreciated.
أن هناك بالفعل نبوغ لم يقدر حق تقديره.
LS: One of my favorite quotes in psychology
لورا: من المقولات المفضلة لدي بعلم النفس
comes from the social psychologist Solomon Asch,
هي لعالم النفس الاجتماعي (سلومون اش)،
and he said the fundamental task of psychology is to remove
ويقول: الدورالأساسي لعلم النفس هو رفع
the veil of self-evidence from things.
حجاب الأدلة القائمة بحد ذاتها عن الأمور.
There are orders of magnitude more decisions you make every day
هناك أوامر عظيمة والمزيد من القرارات التي تقومون بها يومياً
that get the world right.
لفهم العالم بشكل صحيح
You know about objects and their properties.
فتعرف الأشياء وخصائصها.
You know them when they're occluded. You know them in the dark.
تعرفها عندما تكون مخبأة أو في الظلام.
You can walk through rooms.
وتتمكن من عبور الغرف.
You can figure out what other people are thinking. You can talk to them.
ومعرفة ما يفكر فيه الآخرون. والحديث معهم.
You can navigate space. You know about numbers.
يمكنك السفر في الفضاء ومعرفة الأرقام.
You know causal relationships. You know about moral reasoning.
ومعرفة العلاقات السببية والاستدلال الأخلاقي.
You do this effortlessly, so we don't see it,
ولأنك تقوم بذلك بدون عناء، فإننا لا نلاحظ ذلك،
but that is how we get the world right, and it's a remarkable
لكن هكذا نفهم العالم بشكل صحيح، وهذا مدهش
and very difficult-to-understand accomplishment.
وصعب جدًا لفهمه.
CA: I suspect there are people in the audience who have
كريس: أفترض أن هناك أشخاص من الحضور
this view of accelerating technological power
يعتقدون بتسريع القوة التقنية
who might dispute your statement that never in our lifetimes
وقد يعترضون على تصريحك بأن الحاسوب لن يتمكن في حياتنا
will a computer do what a three-year-old child can do,
من فعل ما يقوم به طفل في الثالثه من عمره،
but what's clear is that in any scenario,
لكن من الواضح أنه بغض النظر عن أي سيناريو متوقع،
our machines have so much to learn from our toddlers.
فإن على آلاتنا تعلم الكثير من أطفالنا.
LS: I think so. You'll have some machine learning folks up here.
لورا: صحيح. ستستقبلون هنا بعض القائلين بتعليم الآلة بالطبع.
I mean, you should never bet against babies or chimpanzees
أعني، لا ينبغي عليكم أبداً الرهان ضد الرضع أو الشمبانزي
or technology as a matter of practice,
أو التقنية كمجال تطبيقي،
but it's not just a difference in quantity,
لكن الأمر ليس فقط مجرد فارق في الكمية،
it's a difference in kind.
بل هو فارق في النوع.
We have incredibly powerful computers,
لدينا حواسيب قوية بشكل لا يصدق،
and they do do amazingly sophisticated things,
وتقوم بأمور معقدة بشكل مدهش،
often with very big amounts of data.
غالباً مع معطيات بحجم ضخم.
Human minds do, I think, something quite different,
أما العقل البشري، فأعتقد، أنه يقوم بأمر مختلف تماماً،
and I think it's the structured, hierarchical nature of human knowledge
وأعتقد أن ذلك بفضل المعرفة البشرية ذات الطبيعة التراتبية
that remains a real challenge.
التي تشكل حتى الآن تحدياً حقيقياً لنا.
CA: Laura Schulz, wonderful food for thought. Thank you so much.
كريس: لورا شولز، كان ذلك غذاء رائع للفكر. شكراً جزيلاً لك.
LS: Thank you. (Applause)
لورا: شكراً (تصفيق)